<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-19T10:23:37+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nikhil. R</title><subtitle>Hi! Welcome to my corner on the internet. 
</subtitle><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Gaming - Pre and Post launch checklist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/06/game-metrics-checklist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gaming - Pre and Post launch checklist" /><published>2023-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-07-06T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/06/game-metrics-checklist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/06/game-metrics-checklist.html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a checklist for game developers and product managers to use during the pre-launch period and some important metrics to track immediately post launch. We are assuming that the game has been developed(and tested) and is in the final stages of going live in a single country.</p>

<p>I made this list originally about 8 months back as part of launching PLO at Paytm First Games and have edited it minimally for this blog post.</p>

<h4 id="pre-launch-checklist">Pre launch checklist</h4>

<p>Imagine you are launching a game on Google Play Store. This document gives you a high level checklist to run through to make sure you don’t miss any pre-requisites before your deployment. This is a very generic checklist not specific to a platform or region and this is why you wont see any mention of build file types or translation. Also this is for the final launch not for soft launch and experiments before worldwide publishing. At every step of the checklist ensure that you have a “Final approver” who owns the individual items.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pre-register app campaigns to build up excitement and the rush of install on Day 1. Make sure to open up pre-registration a couple weeks before your launch</li>
  <li>Ensure that you have the game icon, screenshots, advertising banners, social promotional banners, sneak peak trailer, launch video trailer, advertising optimized videos and the emailer/mailing list ready for launch date</li>
  <li>Assuming that QA has signed off on the game(including analytics pipelines/reports testing and game load testing), we should also be doing QA for the banner/video ads, IAP, referral system, app store review system and basically any additional SDK that is baked into the game</li>
  <li>Get a team ready for player support. They should be equipped with FAQs, should be able to answer general queries and available through email and any game forums. Do a CST tool integration also if necessary</li>
  <li>Setup an escalation matrix in case of emergencies for tech, art, server, QA, marketing, acquisition, analytics, live ops legal and the core game</li>
  <li>Research competitors to make sure there aren’t any impending launches coming up around your launch date. Analyze the CPI for various games in the same genre, theme, or even monetization model. Consider your options and budget for promoting, maintaining the game as part of this process.</li>
  <li>Make sure to have your influencer marketing pipeline ready for Day 1 of launch</li>
  <li>Copy/content for keywords, short/long description of the game, emailers (prelaunch and launch), PR, social posts should be ready as well</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="post-launch-tracking">Post launch tracking</h4>

<p>This section of the document deals with some important stuff you should be tracking after your game is launched.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Traffic/Views/Download/Install/Sign up/Finish tutorial (funnel analysis)</li>
  <li>Leads generated from launch campaigns</li>
  <li>Acquisition funnel at a channel level along with promo channel metrics</li>
  <li>Number of downloads</li>
  <li>Cost per install</li>
  <li>User stickiness (DAU/WAU, WAU/MAU). Should also be measured at a channel/affiliate level to measure quality of incoming traffic</li>
  <li>Retention and churn rates (for different time periods)</li>
  <li>Conversion rate,  time to first purchase and average revenue per install</li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/googleplaydev/why-the-first-ten-minutes-is-crucial-if-you-want-to-keep-players-coming-back-to-your-mobile-game-4a89031b6308">Day 1 minutes played vs Day 2 retention</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/googleplaydev/why-focusing-on-tomorrow-brings-back-players-in-the-long-run-e57c51bd3481">DAU return % vs DAU/MAU</a></li>
  <li>Daily revenue (DAU * conversion rate * ARPDAU) and customer lifetime value</li>
  <li>Minutes per day and per session. Also measure time between sessions</li>
  <li>Level progression and retention rates for each level (assuming you have some kind of tiered progression inside the game)</li>
  <li>k-factor (% of referral invites which were accepted and on-boarded). Sort of measures the viral nature of the game</li>
  <li>Customer support ticket reports, IAP reports, daily play store review reports</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a checklist for game developers and product managers to use during the pre-launch period and some important metrics to track immediately post launch. We are assuming that the game has been developed(and tested) and is in the final stages of going live in a single country.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to evaluate a game for your startup?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/14/evaluating-games.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to evaluate a game for your startup?" /><published>2023-05-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-05-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/05/14/evaluating-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/05/14/evaluating-games.html"><![CDATA[<p>As a product manager working in gaming, its impossible to miss the recent rise of multi gaming platforms which package multiple individual games together inside one app. Doing this has a lot of benefits and you can read my previous blog posts to better understand <a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/09/multi-vs-single-gaming.html">how bundling benefits everybody in the ecosystem</a>. In this post, we investigate intrinsic aspects of a game apart from their <strong>powerUser:casualUser</strong> ratio and delve deeper into what makes a game successful by itself. In the previous post, we looked at how different games interact with each other inside a MGP and in this post, we will look at ways in no particular order to evaluate a game in isolation. All games are looked at from a real money gaming POV.</p>

<h5 id="market">Market</h5>

<ul>
  <li>How big is the market currently? How fast is it growing? Ludo was a nascent market couple years ago but it has been growing faster than the rest of the other games in the last couple years. While Poker is an older game, it has been growing slower than the rest of the industry.</li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html">Some notes on RMG market in India</a></li>
  <li>Size of the market would also determine your competition. If you are planning to enter Rummy today, your acquisition costs would be high relatively compared to doing a new game like Carrom.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="learning-curve">Learning Curve</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>There are two important factors here:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Skill vs luck ratio of the game which makes it appealing for a new player(because its winnable) to participate. You want a new player to think that he has a chance at winning at money online.</li>
      <li>Steepness of the learning curve and how long it takes to master the game.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>You ideally want games which are super easy to learn and takes infinite time to master. This will ensure longevity and the game might eventually become a sport.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/lcurve.png" />
</div>

<h5 id="legality-and-regulations">Legality and regulations</h5>

<ul>
  <li>This is actually getting clearer by the day in India. Self Regulatory Organizations (SRO) are going to be established in about 2-3 months. These SRO’s comprised of <a href="https://www.aigf.in/">AIGF</a> + the leading RMG companies from India will determine what is a “skill” game and define frameworks around game certification. Presumably, once certified as a skill game, you should be able to advertise and promote freely everywhere. Overnight bans from different states will reduce and RMG can finally stop being a “gray” market in some jurisdictions.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="familiarity-of-mechanics-or-popularity-of-the-game">Familiarity of mechanics or Popularity of the game</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Games like Rummy and Ludo are culturally familiar to us and thereby also are immensely popular digital games. Ludo has always been in the Top 3 highest grossing casual game on Google Playstore and Rummy RMG has been about 90% of the industry since inception. Almost all RMG games are round off errors (except Fantasy of course) when compared to Rummy.</li>
  <li>This does not mean that you cannot be launching any new game in India. Familiar game mechanics inside a new context (<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.moonactive.coinmaster&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=US">Coinmaster</a> or Striker club (Marvel snap + Fantasy) is one approach as well. You can also look for game inspirations where your current RMG users spend time (like a casino, Win Patti by MPL is an example) or look at casual gaming charts to make RMG variants or create new monetization business models (like PUBG, GGX etc).</li>
  <li><strong>Is there enough power user population for the game?</strong> Can it be a (e)sport someday?</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="monetization-potential">Monetization potential</h5>

<ul>
  <li>As we know in RMG, 80% of our revenue is going to be derived from 20% of your super users. If the game never reaches super user potential and all you can run is Rs.1 loops of the game, you will not be profitable. There should be enough users who have passed your skill(or luck) curve that they are willing to play Rs. 1000 loops of your game. If there is not enough critical mass achievable here, the game won’t work in a RMG setting.</li>
  <li>Alternate monetization angles like collectibles and IAP for free to play games are growing these days too.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="network-effects">Network effects</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Does the game get better with more people playing it? While tournament formats are fueled by compounding network effects, cash game/1v1/ SnG variants don’t benefit as much from more players playing (beyond a point, it doesn’t matter if you have 1000 active players on one stake or 10000 players.). Games where MTTs(or any tournaments) is the main format like Fantasy benefit from this for example.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="variance-in-reward-distribution">Variance in reward distribution</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Variance in nothing but the <em>standard deviation</em> of the players win rate. While the previous skill vs luck discussion tells us about the outcome, variance tells us the distribution of outcome with time</li>
  <li>Some examples of standard deviation for different poker formats: NLH(9max): 60-80 BB/100, PLO 6-max: 120-160 BB/100, PLO Heads up: 220 BB/100. Higher the number, higher the variance. You can see that heads up poker has insanely high variance compared to full ring poker.This basically tells us the randomness of the reward distribution from the average win rate of the player. So, a short heads up session will have a bigger monetary swing compared to a similar session on a full ring (9max) table on an average.</li>
  <li>Higher the variance = higher the wins and losses w.r.t time = more fun for new players</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h4>

<ul>
  <li>In the previous blog, we discussed about how two games interact with each other and in this post, we looked at some ways to evaluate and pick a game for our bundle. Do remember that the games you pick initially and the dimension you focus on to evaluate them would determine your product and strategy. For example, if the game has high power user population, your game discovery should be more towards satisfying their core need/game, skill vs Luck factor of the game would determine your FTUE and how you will deal with the learning curve and cultural significance of the game would determine your GTM etc. Ultimately, your selection of games should determine the product and discovery and not the other way around. I would like to end this post with a rap written by GPT4 summarizing this post.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Gaming startup, gotta evaluate, it’s no fluke,<br />
Check market size, learnin’ curve, and legal rebuke.<br />
Popularity and money, see them in distribution,<br />
High reward variance brings the player’s contribution.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you liked reading this, checkout my other posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/09/multi-vs-single-gaming.html">Do multi gaming apps make sense?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html">Some notes on RMG market in India</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification.html">Make Poker Fun again</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As a product manager working in gaming, its impossible to miss the recent rise of multi gaming platforms which package multiple individual games together inside one app. Doing this has a lot of benefits and you can read my previous blog posts to better understand how bundling benefits everybody in the ecosystem. In this post, we investigate intrinsic aspects of a game apart from their powerUser:casualUser ratio and delve deeper into what makes a game successful by itself. In the previous post, we looked at how different games interact with each other inside a MGP and in this post, we will look at ways in no particular order to evaluate a game in isolation. All games are looked at from a real money gaming POV.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do multi-gaming apps make sense?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/09/multi-vs-single-gaming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do multi-gaming apps make sense?" /><published>2023-04-09T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-09T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/04/09/multi-vs-single-gaming</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/09/multi-vs-single-gaming.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been thinking about multi-gaming platforms due to their recent meteoric rise to <a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html">capture about 10%</a> of the RMG market and the fact that I have to make a decision at work on bundling a mini-game with our main app. The multi-gaming segment is also growing at about 40% y-o-y which is the highest among all RMG segments. While one can argue that this growth was mostly driven by monstrous advertisement spends, this document tries to dig a bit deeper into the user behavior/personas between Multi Gaming Platforms and Single Gaming Platforms, framework to define value of adding/removing each game in the bundle, mental models for packaging games and finally some perspectives on user requirements/needs and way forward for building multi gaming apps. We want to basically explore why everybody is packaging games together or building yet another subscription service?</p>

<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>If you talk to my colleagues at work, they will tell you that I’ve been a fan of single gaming apps and against bundling random games together. I’ve been a power user (was playing <a href="https://www.pokerstars.in/poker/games/omaha/">PLO</a> professionally) and I personally never saw any user (in my bubble) splitting their sessions between playing 500 hands of poker and 100 rounds of rummy. Both are skill games and played with cards but I’ve never seen them played together. If thats the case, why do apps bundle them together? Even worse, they bundle Poker and Fruit Ninja together.</p>

<p>Moreover, given that majority of your revenue is going to come from these power users, I never really understood bundling random games like Fruit Ninja, Ludo etc along with the target game of the power user. In fact, the product folks behind Hike seemed to have reached a similar conclusion. A quote from their post: “Even though we have 10+ games on the platform, most users preferred to play 1 or 2 specific games that they liked the most. Users like to have options but have specific preferences when it comes to actual game play”. You can read the full post <a href="https://blog.hike.in/rush-homescreen-d64a7406dc78">here</a>. Plus, ARPU of single gaming platforms is 3-4x higher than multi-gaming platform. Users seem to spend more on the same game inside the standalone app compared to the multi-gaming app as we can see from the below table:</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/poker.png" height="400" width="650" />
</div>

<p>Given these obvious pros of standalone apps (better ARPU, filled with power users) and cons of multi gaming apps(no obvious user overlap, bad ARPU), why are multi gaming platforms growing? This blog post basically tries to prove the above premise (single gaming is generally better than multi gaming) <b> wrong.</b></p>

<h4 id="content">Content</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Is bundling games good or bad?</li>
  <li>What is a “correct” package of games?</li>
  <li>How to package games?</li>
</ul>

<h4 align="center">Is bundling games good or bad?</h4>

<p>For the rest of the discussion, we will consider these 4 games: Rummy, Poker, Ludo, Fantasy and debate on whether to build a stand alone app or a multi-gaming app comprising all the games. Let’s also split our users and their behavior like this:</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/usertype.png" height="400" width="650" />
</div>

<p>Now that we have our four games and three types of users, lets consider two scenarios:</p>

<p><b>Scenario 1:</b> We build single gaming apps for the games and market them independently. This means, we are primarily trying to attract power users (only fans of Poker would have Poker installed) and will only collect revenue from them. Moreover, a consumer would only have access to game of which they are fans of. They miss out on the other games they otherwise might have played and enjoyed inside a multi-gaming platform. Clearly in this case, we lose out on the casual user revenue if we do single gaming apps and consumers lose out on discovering games they might have liked.</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/gamebundle.png" />
</div>

<p><b>Scenario 2:</b> We build a multi gaming app which has all the games bundled into it. In this scenario, we not only provide power users their favorite game but also allows them access to game they might be “casual users” of. A poker power user might be a “casual user” of Fantasy sports. Also, from a business standpoint, my total addressable market(TAM) is much bigger than my earlier user base because I am now targeting the casual user market of all the games as well.</p>

<p>We can see that, both the platform and the user benefit from multi gaming apps. While the core power user hasn’t changed their behavior much, we have now allowed for casual users to participate and discover new games. Having casual users on the platform is super beneficial especially in real money gaming(RMG) setting where most match-ups are PvP and prizes are pooled in from the players. The utility or value of a gaming network is exponentially proportional to the number of nodes (players) in the network. Once you have a critical mass of users, you can see hyper exponential growth due to the above relationship. Multi-gaming platforms capitalize on these factors to grow fast and big. Clearly, Single Gaming Platform model doesn’t maximize value because power users don’t get games which they maybe interested in and platform providers clearly cannot run a sustainable business without casual users. We can also philosophically say that having <b>multi gaming apps is mostly about serving casual users</b>. (this point will become important towards the end)</p>

<p>Couple things stand out from the above scenarios:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>If you go down the Single Gaming Platform route, you clearly isolate your power users preventing any kind of interaction with casual users. However, power users mainly come for the casual user population to play against and your player volume will suffer. Ultra important for RMG.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Each power user gets access to a platform which has only the game that they wanted. Even if they wanted to try Fantasy sports during cricket season, that isn’t possible</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For example, take the poker variant called Pot Limit Omaha (5card) game. If you ask a random person what it is, you most likely would get a binary answer - either they say that they play the game regularly or ask the full form of the abbreviation. This is because PLO5 has very little casual users - which I believe is attributed to the fact that its never bundled outside of poker apps. A fruit ninja /hyper casual gamer never got PLO5 as part of their Multi Gaming Platforms. However, if you ask a random person if they are a fan of Fantasy sports, the answer this time would fall in a continuous range between a power user(I play every match) to non-user( I’ve tried it once or heard about it somewhere). Fantasy sports certainly has power users but has a big population of casual users too. Interestingly, most of these gamers don’t even know where they started playing Fantasy. It looks like by virtue of signing up for a multi gaming platform, they randomly played a match.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><b><u>Conclusion</u>: Bundling is good for gaming apps when done correctly.</b></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But, what does “correctly” mean? We also know that ARPU suffers from bundling? How do we measure and understand them? Continue reading the next part to know more.</p>

<h4 align="center">What is a "correct" package of games?</h4>

<p>In the previous section, we concluded that bundling games together is beneficial for both the platform and the customer. In this section, we look at some frameworks which will help us decide on which games to add/remove from a bundle? We try to dig deep about what each of our user personas value inside our app and try to look for possible solutions. We also explore some thoughts around evaluating individual games inside a bundle.</p>

<p>By now, most readers of my blog would have understood three basic things about RMG businesses:</p>

<ul>
  <li>85% of money is made from 15% power users</li>
  <li>Power users come to your platform for casual user population</li>
  <li>Recreational users come for big bonuses/awards/prizes/competitions</li>
</ul>

<p><b>Question to the reader:</b> You are a multi-gaming app. You have both Poker and Ludo. They both make the same daily revenue. Which game is better is for the platform? Or in other words, which game is the platform fine with removing?</p>

<p><b>Another question to the reader: </b>You are a multi-gaming app. You are exploring acquiring a game studio and integrate their games into your app. How should both the parties in this transaction think about their decisions?</p>

<p>To answer these questions, we need to define the marginal utility of having the game on the platform. The marginal utility of this game is evaluated based on its ability to acquire new users and retain the existing user base. Or put another way, we should evaluate “how many players would leave my platform, if I remove this game today”? Or from an acquisition POV, “how many players will join my platform if I add this game today?” The quantitative answer to these questions is tightly correlated with the value of the game.</p>

<p>To visualize, this, lets look at at the example between Fantasy and Poker. While Fantasy has lot more users, Poker has higher marginal utility in preventing churn and attracting high value users.</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/usage.png" width="600" />
</div>

<p>For example, lets imagine that if Poker was removed from our multi-gaming app, then 10% of the users would churn. If the overall platform ARPU is about Rs. 300/month and say 1M users play, this would be mean about 100k users churning out, which means a loss of 100k * Rs.300 * 12 (yearly) = Rs. 36Cr/yr in revenue at risk. This means, Poker is valued at about Rs.36Cr to the platform*. This would be somewhat the amount, a gaming studio should be paid yearly if they are running the poker business for multi-gaming app.</p>

<p>Why is Fantasy sports valued at lesser even though it has substantially more usage? Because, the percent of power users who are going to churn out of the app is going to be substantially lesser (Fantasy has a very small power user base). Casual users won’t care much and the platform won’t be affected either.</p>

<p>Lets try to mathematically define this relationship:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><i><b>Value of game to the multi gaming platform = Value of an average user of the platform * Marginal utility of the game in preventing churn.</b></i></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Marginal utility of the game in preventing churn is basically the percentage of people who would churn out if you remove the game from the platform. The idea is that the value of the game is related to its impact on EVERY user of the platform. In some sense, we are distributing the power user value of the multi-gaming platform into the broader population of casual users and non-users of the platform. We are exposing them to these games for free which they otherwise would never have found on their own. Finally, to exactly calculate the value of the game, you should remove it from your app, calculate the customers you will lose and establish the revenue loss due to it.</p>

<p>However, this approach is not exactly practical. I cannot remove a game from my app tomorrow to prove that it has value. For a company/product manager to do this exercise, we need an alternate approach to define value of the game. Remember that earlier, I had mentioned that from an acquisition POV, value of a game is the “number of new users” it will bring to the platform because of its addition.</p>

<p>Lets again take the Poker example to explain this situation. I am trying to decide on including Poker into my Multi Gaming Platform. Lets assume that the value of the game standalone is X(whatever an individual game studio makes running it alone). So, if I have to think about integrating poker, how much extra revenue/value would I get? The answer definitely cannot be equal to X. To figure this out, we first need to understand our current user base and how it will overlap with Poker in the first place. Does adding this game unlock an entirely new Total addressable market (TAM) for me? or the players of this new game are already my customers?</p>

<p>Lets consider two extreme scenarios to answer these questions:</p>

<p><b>Case 1:</b> Fully overlapped power user base. Remember, we inherently assume that single gaming apps are composed of power users only(refer to the first section of this post for clarity). This means, all the power users of poker are already an user of the Multi Gaming Platform.</p>

<p>To elaborate further, lets assume that the multi gaming app has 1M users with Rs. 300/month as ARPU. Poker standalone has 250k users with ARPU of Rs. 400/month. In this case of full overlap between the power user base, all these 250k Poker users are already a customer of the multi gaming app. They are poker power users but playing some casual game inside the multi gaming app for now.</p>

<p>In this case, so how much does the platform expect to make when they integrate/launch poker? They are still going to have the same amount of users but they with the addition of poker, the power users get activated(they were casual users before) and start playing the game inside the multi gaming app. A lot of casual users are now getting exposed to poker and power users have increased engagement inside multi-gaming app because they now have their favorite game as well. Power users like the fact that the game is bundled and they don’t have to split their deposits between two platforms and thereby have higher retention too. While some value is getting created, its hard to quantify.</p>

<p>However, this is the worst scenario and adds very little value to the platform. Lets look at the other case.</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/overlap.png" height="400" width="650" />
</div>

<p><b>Case 2:</b>Zero overlap between power user base. This means, all the poker power users are isolated and currently don’t play inside the Multi Gaming Platform. They only play on their standalone poker app. From the platforms POV, this is exciting because of new addition of all these power users who are now coming to your Multi Gaming Platform for the game plus the fact that existing customers of Multi Gaming Platform get Poker for free(without installing any extra app). This contributes to direct increase in revenue.</p>

<p>To elaborate further, lets assume that the multi gaming app has 1M users with Rs. 300/month as ARPU. Poker standalone has 250k users with ARPU of Rs. 400/month. Lets look at this integration form the eyes of both the platform and poker standalone app.</p>

<p>Platform: They get these 250k new users directly and get Rs. 300 * 250k = Rs. 7.5Cr per month extra. If you go back to my first equation which is <i>value of game to the multi gaming platform = Value of an average user of the platform * Marginal utility of the game in preventing churn</i> and plug the numbers, power users who will leave the platform if you remove the game =  value of game (Rs. 7.5cr)/Rs. 300 = 25% This is the percent of the user base which will churn out if you remove Poker which is about 250k users.</p>

<p>Poker standalone: They were making Rs. 10cr earlier, but the platform has assigned a value of only Rs. 7.5cr to it which means they obviously won’t agree with this integration. So, why where will the extra 2.5cr come from? Where is the calculation issue?</p>

<p>To understand this, we need a different way for the platform to calculate value of poker (post integration). They cannot simple use old ARPU numbers. Lets double click on this thought and try to define a practical mathematical relationship:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><b><i>Value of game to the platform = Value of power user (ARPU) of standalone app* percentage of customers who are power users of your game inside the Multi Gaming Platform post integration</i></b></p>
</blockquote>

<p><i>Note: LHS of both equations is same.(this will matter later on).If you integrate Poker and 100% of your users become power users of poker, your platform will basically have same value as a standalone app. If nobody becomes a power user, then value of Poker is zero for the platform.</i></p>

<p>Assuming 25% of them convert to power users inside the app, now the value of the game to the platform = 250k users * Rs. 400 (new power user ARPU) = Rs. 10Cr. Now they can happily pay the 10Cr that the standalone app wants.</p>

<p>This is the best scenario that the platform as well as the poker standalone app wants. Everybody makes more or equal money than they made before.</p>

<p>Great!. We have established some equations for defining value of a game inside a multi-gaming platform. However, this section started with the promise of teaching you to find the “optimal” packaging of games.</p>

<p>We introduced two ways to define value of a game. One is through understanding churn and another is through understand acquisition. Now, if we equate both sides of this equation, we have:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><i>Value of an average user in Multi Gaming Platform * Marginal utility of the game in preventing churn = Value of power user (ARPU) of standalone app* percentage of customers who are power users of your game inside the Multi Gaming Platform post integration</i></p>
</blockquote>

<p>When both the previous equations match, the platform packaging the game and the game provider are in equilibrium. Both of their interests get satisfied and it makes logical sense to package the game instead of running it standalone. I would call this bundle of games “correct”.This summary is interesting because Power user% (RHS) is easer to understand and measure compared to “marginal utility in preventing churn”. For the latter, you can just look at a standalone Poker app for proxy (assuming these newly converted power users will behave the same as standalone app users) but for the former, you will have to remove Poker from a Multi Gaming Platform to measure it accurately.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Conclusion: We defined what an optimal bundling of games should look like and various parameters affecting it. We came up with an interesting equation which can be used to form mental models regarding relationships about games and how they interact with game bundles.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But what is the implication of this equation? What does it mean for the kind of games I have to choose for my bundle? Is Poker + Ludo a better bundle or Poker + Rummy? Continue reading to answer these questions.</p>

<h4 align="center">How to package games? </h4>

<p>In first section, we concluded that, Bundling games is good when done “correctly” and in the second section we defined how to quantify what a correct bundle looks like. Now that we have concluded that we have to bundle games, we need to establish a framework around choosing and picking games to bundle inside a Multi Gaming Platform.</p>

<p>Lets start with the commonly established logic. You should pick and pack games which have the least amount of power user overlap and maximum amount of casual user overlap. This means, you package Poker along with card games but not with candy crush/wordle/bubble shooter etc. This also makes logical sense and I was a firm believer of this as well.</p>

<p>However, this section we try to determine if this is actually true and if you should actually bundle Poker with something like another card game/chess or wordle/racing game/etc.</p>

<p>Lets go back to the second section, where we were trying to ascertain what the game vs game bundle relationship looks like. Lets restate the equation here again:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><i>Value of an average user in Multi Gaming Platform * Marginal utility of the game in preventing churn = Value of power user (ARPU) of standalone app* percentage of customers who are power users of your game inside the Multi Gaming Platform post integration</i></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We ascertained that the packaging of games will be optimal(Case 2 is best scenario to package) when there was a completely distinct power user base. The power user base of poker is being used to it maximum value by adding new customers to the platform. In the above equation, given that ARPU of users are unaffected (for our purposes), we can observe that the extra utility of having power user in the platform(preventing churn) is becoming equal to the percentage of customers who are power users of the game inside the Multi Gaming Platform.</p>

<p>So, what does it mean? We have proved that adding a game which already has power user overlap with your app is not the most ideal but rather adding a game which has the least overlap is beneficial. Why though? as you can see below, from the perspective of an user, if you are a power user of rummy or poker or ludo, the Multi Gaming Platform is a good value. From the platforms POV, it gets to add new users because of adding the extra game. From the customers POV, if they are a power user of either Poker or Rummy or Ludo, the app is a good deal. You can the Shishir’s post linked at the bottom for a generalized explanation of this behavior.</p>

<p>Now if the Multi Gaming Platform is already valuable to the user (they installed it for some game of which they are a power user of), they will not care about adding another game to it. The value of the app for the power user comes only from their target game. So, you are better off adding a game that someone else (ideally a non-user) would be a power user of instead of adding another similar game.</p>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/mgp.png" height="400" width="650" />
</div>

<p>The customer will see value in the Multi Gaming Platform compared to the Single Gaming Platform if</p>

<ul>
  <li>it has the game he is a power user of</li>
  <li>product experience of that game is equal to Single Gaming Platform</li>
  <li>it has at least one more game that he is a casual user of, that he wants to play. (else he will install the standalone app only)</li>
</ul>

<p>To take this to an extreme, the best multi gaming platform would have all the games its users are power users of. Everyone gets their favorite game and also gets access to a game there are casual users of(1 game per user basically). If there are no casual users (meaning, I play only one game), then this is no worse than installing the game separately. But any amount of casual user overlap will justify the packaging of games. Fundamentally, this basically tells that multi gaming apps is more about providing value for casual users than power users.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Conclusion: Add games which have minimum power user overlap and maximum casual user overlap. This is why Poker + Ludo is better than Poker + Rummy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This section is the most counter intuitive of all the other sections. Because, we basically concluded that we should be adding games which are diverse and have the least amount of power user overlap. Does this mean, I will add a racing game to my Poker platform? Short answer is yes, but with some nuances. It is hard to market super diverse bundles. If very hard to market a poker + racing Multi Gaming Platform compared to poker+rummy Multi Gaming Platform. But that is just a marketing challenge because we now know for a fact that our games have to super diverse and minimize power user overlap. Same reason Amazon is bundling Prime Video with fast shipping. To summarize :</p>

<ul>
  <li>Put together a list of games with minimum power user overlap and maximum casual user overlap</li>
  <li>Ensure that there is no downgrade in user experience for power users in each of these games</li>
  <li>Show users only the games that they are likely to be a power user of</li>
  <li>Make sure there is clear integration value and the app is overall coherent.</li>
</ul>

<p><b><i><u>Final thoughts</u></i></b></p>

<p>Bundling is a natural evolution for many businesses and can lead to increased productivity and value. Amazon, Netflix, McDonald’s, etc all use it to their advantage and continue to add very diverse items into their bundles. Netflix has games. McDonald’s hands out toys with burgers and the Amazon Prime package is massive and diverse.</p>

<p>However, we should be cautious as well. There are some unmeasured factosr which I have omitted in the article like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>conversion% of power users after you integrate may not be 100%</li>
  <li>power user behavior can change with time (influenced by losing money)</li>
  <li>matching product experiences between SGP and MGP is hard</li>
  <li>this framework doesn’t work if the ARPU difference is very high between the game and the platform</li>
</ul>

<p>This framework can be applied to more general product development, such as contemplating which set of features to put behind a subscription service. You can use this framework to decide the marginal utility of any single feature/product. Bundles of the future will be larger and more diverse than what we have today because packaging has a natural economy of scale attached to it. It is much easier to go from 100M users to 101M users than it is to go from 0 to 1M users. This is largely caused by casual user overlap (there are no 100M power users) - the larger your bundle, the more casual users you can amortize costs between and faster you grow.</p>

<p>If you liked reading this post, please share it with your product and business friends and checkout my other posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/15/gtoinspector-startup.html">GTO Inspector - My attempt at building an online business</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html">Some notes on RMG market in India</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification.html">Make Poker Fun again</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Further Reading and Sources:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://repositorio.ucp.pt/bitstream/10400.14/26226/1/152116038%20Marta%20Gomes%20W.pdf">The effect of anchoring in product bundles</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2489825">How Buyers Evaluate Product Bundles: A Model of Anchoring and Adjustment</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://coda.io/@shishir/four-myths-of-bundling">Shishir Mehrotra’s post on bundling in general</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://cdixon.org/2012/07/08/how-bundling-benefits-sellers-and-buyers">The OG Chris Dixon post on “How bundling benefits sellers and buyers”</a></li>
</ul>

<p>*Do notice the fact that we aren’t talking about game revenues here but some intrinsic concept called “value of the game” which we are trying to define.</p>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve been thinking about multi-gaming platforms due to their recent meteoric rise to capture about 10% of the RMG market and the fact that I have to make a decision at work on bundling a mini-game with our main app. The multi-gaming segment is also growing at about 40% y-o-y which is the highest among all RMG segments. While one can argue that this growth was mostly driven by monstrous advertisement spends, this document tries to dig a bit deeper into the user behavior/personas between Multi Gaming Platforms and Single Gaming Platforms, framework to define value of adding/removing each game in the bundle, mental models for packaging games and finally some perspectives on user requirements/needs and way forward for building multi gaming apps. We want to basically explore why everybody is packaging games together or building yet another subscription service?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some notes on Real Money Gaming (RMG) in India</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some notes on Real Money Gaming (RMG) in India" /><published>2023-04-03T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-03T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/04/03/gaming-state-india.html"><![CDATA[<p>The gaming industry in India has been growing exponentially in recent years, with many people joining the ranks of avid and serious players. India has now become one of the leading countries in the world in terms of gaming, and this is largely due to the large population, the availability of technology, and the increasing enthusiasm and accessibility of gaming platforms. With more and more people playing games, India has become a massive and vibrant gaming community, with people of all ages and backgrounds enjoying the many styles and genres of gaming. From console and PC gaming, to mobile and online gaming, there is something for everyone to enjoy in India’s gaming scene. This post mostly focusses on the real money gaming market, potential profit pool and if somebody is starting a RMG company in India - this document can serve as a preliminary primer in understanding the market.</p>

<p><u>High level Index:</u></p>

<ol>
  <li>Why bother building in India in the first place?</li>
  <li>What is the current market scenario in India?
    <ul>
      <li>How is the entire gaming industry revenue split?</li>
    </ul>
    <ul>
      <li>Where is majority of the revenue and profit potential?</li>
      <li>Which sub vertical is growing?
        <ul>
          <li>What are users majorly playing?</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Where is the market opportunity?
    <ul>
      <li>Differentiator for RMG companies starting today and path forward for building a RMG business</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h4 id="1-why-india">1. Why India?</h4>

<h5 id="bull-case-for-gaming-in-india">Bull case for gaming in India</h5>

<ul>
  <li>About $3Bn market size but having consistent growth. RMG dominates about 55% of this</li>
  <li>Cheap data/ digital payment penetration</li>
  <li>90% users play on a mobile phone and entry level smartphones are some of the cheapest in the world</li>
  <li>Growing youth population. Already the youngest population which overlaps greatly with the target demographic for gaming. About 400Mn gamers today is the conservative estimate</li>
  <li>This photo illustrate the growing internet user base leading to growing number of gamers » growing number of paid gamers</li>
</ul>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/funnel.png" height="400" width="650" />
</div>

<ul>
  <li>Among this - about 110Mn are paying gamers which includes RMG + IAP + subscriptions.
    <ul>
      <li>This number is set to double along with ARPU according to Redseer (by basically benchmarking with US/China)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>90% of them are mobile based. 90% revenue also comes in mobile.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Demand side plus points</p>

    <ul>
      <li><strong>Affinitly/Aspiration to make money/win money online is high for our demographic. Aspirational youth population.</strong></li>
      <li>Rising disposable income. Lot of this 400Mn gamers are in Tier 1-2 cities</li>
      <li>Time spent in gaming rivals OTT/Social. About 3.1hrs per week</li>
      <li>Power user retention and LTV is comparable to international platforms. Example: 20% of MAU of Adda52 are players who are &gt; 3 years old on the platform.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<div align="center">
<img src="/assets/files/timespent.png" height="400" width="550" />
</div>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Supply side</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Rich cultural history leading to lot of familiar homegrown titles. Rummy is about 85% of the RMG market which in turn is about 55% of the overall gaming market</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/revenuesplit.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>

<ul>
  <li>Multi gaming platforms (MGP’s) still haven’t exactly cracked the unit economics for hyper casual games but they at least bring in DAU</li>
  <li>Rising consumer trust in online platforms and digital payments</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="bull-case-for-building-outside-india">Bull case for building outside India?</h5>

<ul>
  <li>ARPU is much higher outside India. While you can argue that the core power user ARPU is comparable, the number of them playing these games for a living/seriously is very little. Check out <a href="/2022/06/15/gtoinspector-startup.html">this post</a> for more about this set of these power users in India</li>
  <li>Conversion % for casual is ridiculously low in India. About 60% of non-RMG is ad supported</li>
  <li>Regulation for a lot of real money games is unclear. SRO’s (self regulatory organizations) still haven’t been formed and states banning betting overnight is an existential risk.</li>
  <li>Multi gaming platforms haven’t solved for retention thereby leading to unsustainable unit economics for most games (churn is especially higher for the hyper casual real money games).It is still a problem plaguing the industry</li>
  <li>Certain companies have advertising monopolies. Acquisition is expensive compared to the LTV that 80% of the customers offer</li>
  <li>Changing perspective about skill games and their money making potential. People no longer view them as gambling but rather as legitimate career options. Money making potential for certain games like poker in Indian rivals an executive salary at FAANG.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="2-indian-gaming-market">2. Indian Gaming Market</h4>

<h5 id="revenue-split">Revenue Split</h5>

<p>RMG dominates the market account for about 55-60% of the overall revenue. While casual games attract the largest number of users and have been crucial in growing the mobile gaming culture in India, while real money gaming attracts the highest paying users in mobile gaming. As a result, real money games have been the largest revenue source for India’s gaming sector. This segment is expected to grow at 30% CAGR with growing expectation of regulatory clarity.</p>

<h6 id="rmg-vs-non-rmg">RMG vs Non-RMG</h6>

<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/rmg.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>

<p>Online RMG market is segmented into 3 game types (Online Rummy, Poker &amp; Fantasy Sports) and by
platforms into Single game (&gt;91%) &amp; Multi game (~9%) - collectively growing at a CAGR of ~61% for the last 3 years. Online Real Money Gaming Market split by the following segments :</p>

<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/rmggrowth.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>
<p>Rummy is currently the largest segment and is expected to dominate the RMG market in the future due to rising number of new rummy users from north India and increasing propensity to pay of existing users. Rummy market is expected to increase from $1Bn in FY2022 to $2.4Bn-$2.5Bn in FY2026 at CAGR of 24%.</p>

<p>Poker has the least penetration when compared to rummy and fantasy, indicating a very high potential for growth in the coming years. Poker has the highest user retention rate and highest revenue per user among the two games considered here. Poker market is expected to grow from $150Mn in FY2022 to $450Mn in FY2026.</p>

<h6 id="inside-non-rmg-where-is-the-money-coming-from">Inside Non-RMG, where is the money coming from?</h6>

<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/nonrmg.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>

<p>Lets now move on how the users are split between RMG vs Non-RMG. The Non-RMG market has two major categories in terms of game types - Casual and Hyper-casual, and core games. Casual and Hyper casual games offer a quick and easy means to pass time and have become a popular entry point for India’s first-time mobile gamers. As a result, this segment has the highest number of overall users, i.e. 350-420 Mn, with very low paid user conversion rate (8-10%). Also, there are around 150-160 Mn core game users with very high conversion of paid gamers (36-43%)</p>
<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/usersplit.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>

<p>RMG witnesses a MACU of 12-13 Mn of the total 26-30 Mn real money gamers and it is expected to reach 60- 80 Mn real money gamers in the upcoming years.</p>

<p>Everything else like e-sports, desktop, platforms are rounding off errors at the moment. E-sports grew about 5x on a small base but has plateaued since.</p>

<h5 id="multi-gaming-vs-single-gaming-platforms">Multi Gaming vs Single Gaming platforms</h5>

<p>While Single Game Platforms (SGP) currently dominate the market with (~90%) market share; the upcoming format of Multi-game platforms (MGP) may get popular in the future. MGPs offer a wider variety of games to users; and are therefore able to attract gamers from a wider set of interests and abilities. It should conceptually also be able retain them more by keeping them entertained and engaged for a longer time due to the wide array of game offerings (in reality however, this is harder than it looks).</p>

<p>The recent rise of MGP can be attributed to greater game types attracting wider variety of audiences(thereby increasing reach), distributed game dev costs and ability to capitalize on cross game synergies. <b>In its current state, MGP is growing at ~40%; which is the highest across various segments of RMG; and is expected to be ~12% of the market by 2026. While, the relative share appears low, in absolute terms this translates to nearly $500Mn (viz. ~4x in 5 years) by 2026. This explains the observed interest amongst gaming companies to explore and grow as Multi-gaming Platforms.</b></p>

<p>MGP’s have also really lowered customer acquisition costs by spreading it and averaging it between low CAC games like Fantasy/Ludo and high LTV games like Poker/Rummy etc. However, not all things with MGP’s are positive. Majority of the users still go to these app to <a href="https://blog.hike.in/rush-homescreen-d64a7406dc78">play 1-2 games</a> and don’t deviate beyond them. Habit forming for the rest of the games is still a hit or miss.</p>

<h4 id="3-some-perspective-on-rmggaming-and-way-forward">3. Some perspective on RMG/gaming and way forward</h4>

<p><b>How are these RMG businesses differentiated? </b></p>

<p>RMG has more or less become a commodity business. Most products look the same and some companies even modify their GTM to match competitors in hopes of attracting users with a familiar platform and better deposit offers(like a <a href="https://finematics.com/vampire-attack-sushiswap-explained/">vampire attack</a>). Product innovation has been slow or non-existent in this industry for the last ten years. Adda52 from 2013 looks 90% same as today. Moreover, given the extremely low M12 retention rates, you have to keep acquiring users (spending money) every year as your platform churns through them - making this a treadmill business.</p>

<p>Core problems to solve for in RMG:</p>

<ul>
  <li>LTV/CAC doesn’t work
    <ul>
      <li>High acquisition costs but low average LTV. For example: CAC for acquiring poker players is about Rs. 15k and its impossible to make this money back if 75% of your new users churn out before 3 months. This problem has to be solved from both ends by lower acquisition costs and improving retention</li>
      <li>Possible solution: Mini game casual variants of popular card games with shorter game loops would set the product apart in terms of giving new users a feel and taste of the game related wagering/betting while at the same time without diluting the skill aspect.
        <ul>
          <li><a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.simpleviralgames.timepass">Timepass.Games</a> is doing this for hyper casual games in a TikTok variant. Idea is to engage the user for longer by giving them multiple games in quick shorter formats</li>
          <li>There are some caveats to making RMG games in shorter formats. As a rule of thumb in RMG businesses, 80% of your revenue comes from 15% of your users. This ratio is extreme for some games like poker and normalized for bigger games like Fantasy. If you reduce the game loop duration, its very hard to have the same ARPU as earlier and retention is still an open problem with hyper casual variants. Having tight game loops along with strong product driven conversion milestones to make the user play the longer variant could alleviate some of these concerns.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Poor retention</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>In my own experience, the single biggest factor determining the retention of a player is their loss rate(money lost /day). If a player loses money on the platform, he/she is prone to churn. This is unfortunately unstoppable in the RMG business because of its design. However, we can explore couple solutions:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Make losing money for new players slower and more enjoyable. At the end of the day, 95% of your players are going to lose money. Giving them a fun and interactive experience lowers chances of churn. Kickass FTUE teaching the players to make sure they learn the rules before wagering is key as well.</li>
          <li>Re-acquiring them again using a network site model. This is an under explored concept in India where multiple website skins could share liquidity of players. This way, you can have a gamified skin of the game marketed towards one target group and serious/pro friendly version marketed towards a different set of users. They can share player liquidity across all games while still having different fee/reward structures. Taj Rummy/Poker is doing this to some extent with a very bad product at the moment in India but there are no big name players yet. Gameskraft has brilliantly marketed 4 different Rummy versions which all share liquidity to keep re-acquiring their churned out users for cheap.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>At the end of the day, majority of your revenue comes from power users who choose your platform primarily for player liquidity and product experience. Recreational users are attracted towards big offers and guarantees but churn out when they lose. Ensuring you can retain/re-acquire recreational users through strong data driven offers/loops and providing superior gaming experience to power users would lead to a sustainable RMG business in my opinion. However, having a great product by itself is not enough. Distribution is super critical and making sure you can acquire users for cheap makes or breaks a platform. Cross game analytics/anti fraud/rewards (which is by large forgotten by most companies) is paramount to predict and minimize churn.</p>

<p>Revenue comparison between some Indian and foreign betting companies shows the market potential for a mature player globally:</p>

<div align="center">

<img src="/assets/files/comp.png" height="400" width="500" />

</div>
<p><u><b>Sources</b></u></p>

<ul>
  <li>Delta Tech(Adda52) DRHP</li>
  <li>Nazara gaming DRHP</li>
  <li>Redseer, BCG and Newzoo research reports</li>
  <li>Lumikai and Konvoy VC blogs</li>
</ul>

<p>If you liked this, checkout my other related posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/15/gtoinspector-startup.html">GTO Inspector - My attempt at building an online business</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification.html">Make Poker Fun again</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/09/tornado-cash-block.html">We should all have something to hide - Tornado cash takedown</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The gaming industry in India has been growing exponentially in recent years, with many people joining the ranks of avid and serious players. India has now become one of the leading countries in the world in terms of gaming, and this is largely due to the large population, the availability of technology, and the increasing enthusiasm and accessibility of gaming platforms. With more and more people playing games, India has become a massive and vibrant gaming community, with people of all ages and backgrounds enjoying the many styles and genres of gaming. From console and PC gaming, to mobile and online gaming, there is something for everyone to enjoy in India’s gaming scene. This post mostly focusses on the real money gaming market, potential profit pool and if somebody is starting a RMG company in India - this document can serve as a preliminary primer in understanding the market.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Classifying 2022 DeFi protocols</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/enhancer-compounder.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Classifying 2022 DeFi protocols" /><published>2023-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2023-01-26T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/enhancer-compounder</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/26/enhancer-compounder.html"><![CDATA[<p>DeFi in 2022 was a lot about liquidity provisioning and balance sheet monetization. Everybody was looking for simple and safe yields without the risk of getting their hands burnt. The year has brought the dawn of certain type of protocols like:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Automation protocols for auto-compounding funds</li>
  <li>Enhancers for looping funds</li>
  <li>Extender protocols</li>
</ul>

<p>Automation protocols re-balance liquidity positions across AMMs and Layer 1s, recycle rewards, and provide “auto-compounding” services. Convex Finance is one the leading examples - they “recycle” $CRV and Curve LP tokens for boosted rewards, trading fees, and governance tokens.</p>

<p>Enhancers are protocols that do not introduce new operating models for DeFi, but rather recycle the outputs from existing protocols to optimize returns for the end user. A good example of this is <a href="https://abracadabra.money/">Abracadabra.money</a>, which is similar to MakerDAO but with the important difference that it creates collateralized debt position from yield-bearing assets (and has much looser risk controls).</p>

<p>Extenders are protocols that stack various underlying DeFi protocols. Alchemix is a good example. It’s
vaults function similarly to MakerDAO’s, but the protocol also rehypothecates its collateral assets and
deposits them into yield aggregators like Yearn, creating yield generating synthetic tokens which look like “self-repaying loans.” The rehypothecation creates risk, as the protocol absorbs the risks of the lower-level protocols it’s built on. Still, self-repaying loans!</p>

<p>Checkout my other related posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/09/tornado-cash-block.html">We should all have something to hide - Tornado cash takedown</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/28/defi-user-journey.html">Problem statements to solve for a retail investor in DeFi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives.html">Option protocols in DeFi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/27/web3-gaming.html">Blockchain gaming - Current state</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[DeFi in 2022 was a lot about liquidity provisioning and balance sheet monetization. Everybody was looking for simple and safe yields without the risk of getting their hands burnt. The year has brought the dawn of certain type of protocols like:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The magic words are squeamish ossifrage</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/10/12/wolfram-crypto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The magic words are squeamish ossifrage" /><published>2022-10-12T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-10-12T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/10/12/wolfram-crypto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/10/12/wolfram-crypto.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>“The Magic Words are Squeamish Ossifrage” was the solution to a challenge ciphertext posed by the inventors of the RSA cipher in 1977</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Howdy! I have been bit busy with launching Pot limit Omaha ( a poker variant) at work and haven’t been able to write regularly. Launching PLO is extra special for me because it sort of makes my poker journey go full circle. From playing PLO professionally, to building products for professional PLO players to finally launching a PLO product as part of a poker website itself; its been a fun ride.</p>

<p>I was part of the Wolfram Summer school which ran during the summers of 2017 in the town of Boston, MA where I built a network sniffer function for their core product. It was a super hectic summer for me where I was simultaneously working on three different projects. I was attending the summer school in USA, doing my second GSoc project ( writing a HTTP2.0 implementation for a network lib) and was also part of the OWASP Code Sprint (worked on a tool for obfuscating assembly shellcodes). In hindsight, I learned an immense amount over the summer while also travelling around New York.</p>

<p>At the start of the summer school, we were asked to pick a topic and write a computational essay to get familiar with the basic functions of Mathematica. I wrote about the basic RSA system. The essay is embedded below. Feel free to run the code yourself.</p>

<p>More details on my summer school work can be found <a href="https://education.wolfram.com/summer-school/alumni/2017/ramesh/">here</a></p>

<iframe width="800" height="6500" src="https://www.wolframcloud.com/obj/summerschool/pages/2017/NikhilRamesh_TE" frameborder="0"></iframe>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“The Magic Words are Squeamish Ossifrage” was the solution to a challenge ciphertext posed by the inventors of the RSA cipher in 1977]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A take on web3/DeFi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/my-take-crypto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A take on web3/DeFi" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/my-take-crypto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/09/01/my-take-crypto.html"><![CDATA[<p>Most use cases for crypto are in an imaginary space. Lot of the details like “why does the customer care?”, “why will they pay for it?”, etc are not necessarily thought out clearly. Most products ask me to “Imagine a world where everything is de-centralized”.</p>

<p>So, what do I think will come out of web3/DeFi mania?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>First off, currently crypto and web3 is really great currently for trading/speculation related use cases. Solving for capital efficiency, security, infra makes sense in long term.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Then what? Retail investors? Gaming? NFT/Collectibles? Countries run as DAO’s?  Its very hard to come up with future (&gt;10yr) use cases but we can look at some analogies.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Comparison with Internet:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Commonly used in super bullish crypto circles, the comparison has some rough edges. Internet started as a way for education/military bases to talk to each other. It started from day 1 solving for a single use case(comms) only instead of 1000 other possible things you can build on top of it. While it didn’t have distribution initially, it took like 15-20 years for apps to go mainstream. People kept building iteratively on top of it.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>While it may work as a great branding for VC’s, here it just becomes a speculating exercise on potential use cases 10yrs down the line. This is sort of the reverse order as the internet. Imagine somebody trying to raise money for Snapchat in 1990.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>If you have to borrow analogies from the internet, solving for infra and for specific user personas/use cases today makes the most sense. The internet did it for 15years for some niche user personas.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>In web3, we started <strong>directly</strong> with a compelling vision of no single counter party/no centralised institutions/everybody owns everything/trust less/permission less and then tried to work backwards into solving for use cases.
    <ul>
      <li>Funnily, most successful crypto companies are currently centralised. While starting like this isn’t necessarily bad, lot of them are not on a path to de-centralisation.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>There is definitely some value in the space. Expectations are currently super high to become a $100 Billion business for everybody but today, it may just be a $1 Billion niche for the time being. When you pump $50 Billion into the ecosystem, it makes it hard to differentiate between utility vs speculation vs any other perverse incentives. Some products assume PMF because of wash trading/bots etc. If you look at the top gas spenders on AVAX/Polygon, it’s mostly bots inside a game or wash trading NFTs. Ponzi schemes, unnatural yields through looping money around etc have become commonplace too.</li>
  <li>It may solve for some specific use cases in the future like remittances (cross border payments, a $5 billion use case ) or market making/infra for trading which is again maybe a $30 Billion business.</li>
</ul>

<p>I hope in the future, we can solve legitimate problems with this tech. Luckily since this space basically speed runs through everything, the cycle length to actual mass products may not be as long as the internet.</p>

<p>Checkout my other related posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/09/tornado-cash-block.html">We should all have something to hide - Tornado cash takedown</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/28/defi-user-journey.html">Problem statements to solve for a retail investor in DeFi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives.html">Option protocols in DeFi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/27/web3-gaming.html">Blockchain gaming - Current state</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Most use cases for crypto are in an imaginary space. Lot of the details like “why does the customer care?”, “why will they pay for it?”, etc are not necessarily thought out clearly. Most products ask me to “Imagine a world where everything is de-centralized”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Problem statements to solve for a retail investor in DeFi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/28/defi-user-journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Problem statements to solve for a retail investor in DeFi" /><published>2022-08-28T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-08-28T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/28/defi-user-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/28/defi-user-journey.html"><![CDATA[<p>The first section of the article inspects the various user personas interacting with DeFi protocols and their individual requirements. The second section  identifies various products which solve for these use cases. We mostly look for on-chain use cases which already have a reasonable amount of adoption. This post simply surfaces the various participants across the value chain and identifies open problems. Some cutting-edge novel cases with nascent adoption might get overlooked. Nevertheless, we keep an eye out for unsolved/potential growth segments and see what we can build there.</p>

<h5 id="user-personas">User Personas</h5>

<p>Broad retail requirements for interacting with financial services and products can be classified as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Investing</li>
  <li>Speculating/Trading</li>
  <li>Remittances</li>
  <li>Bill/Utility payments</li>
  <li>Commerce
    <ul>
      <li>Collectibles</li>
      <li>Shopping</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Gaming</li>
  <li>Entertainment
    <ul>
      <li>Social</li>
      <li>Content</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Transfers (P2P)/Cross border payments
    <ul>
      <li>Want to transfer money to somebody instantaneously with the lowest fees.</li>
      <li>User Requirement and priorities
        <ul>
          <li>Easy on-off ramp</li>
          <li>Global availability</li>
          <li>Access to Payment rails</li>
          <li>Network of peers/merchants already on-boarded into the network
            <ul>
              <li>Chicken/egg problem</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Trust /Safety</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>New user personas who may start using on-chain products. The requirements for those users would be different and dependent on what use case they on-board for.
    <ul>
      <li>For example, my mom started using online payments (UPI) after Quick commerce (10min delivery) became commonplace).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Currently, the first two user personas (<strong>Investor and the speculator</strong>) are the most common place in DeFi. In fact every other use case is in fact a minority. Lets look at them deeper.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Average investor</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Speculator/ trader</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Wants economic exposure to DeFi. Is not every sophisticated, intends to make +ve ROI, wants an engaging experience.</td>
      <td>Wants a platform get access to capital and trade/gamble. High returns on capital is the ultimate priority.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>Product requirements</em><br /><br />    - Savings<br />    - Investing<br />    - Lending/Borrowing<br />    - Insurance</td>
      <td><em>Product Requirements</em><br /><br />    - Investing<br />    - Trading across asset classes <br />    - Coin/NFT launchpads<br />    - Credit (Lending/Borrowing/Leverage)<br />    - Other financial products (derivatives/swaps/bonds/etc)<br />    - Insurance<br />    - Data and Analytics</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><em>First priorities</em><br /><br />    - Easy on-ramp and off-ramp<br />  - High yield products<br />     - Minimal friction while adding/removing/transferring/spending money<br />      - KYC/Identity<br />      - Regulatory/Compliance and clarity<br />      - Taxation/Ease of filing<br />    - Trust/Safety in the platform<br />    - Principal protection (low volatility) for investment products<br />    - Easy to use (non complicated) UX<br />      -  Wants a personalized UX which is engaging as well as efficient<br />    - Easy Access everywhere (on mobile while travelling)<br />    - Speed of transactions have to instantaneous <br />    - (Single preferably) centralized market place/platform access to all products<br />      - Variety of markets available<br />    - Custody/Asset management<br />    - Cheap transaction costs<br />    - Best APR/APY (for savings/investments) and credit products<br />    - Easy onboarding</td>
      <td><em>First priorities</em><br /><br />  - Everything from Average investor<br />     - Advanced feature rich snappy UX <br />      - Portfolio management<br />     - Strategy builder<br />  - Risk Management<br />   - Centralized market place/platform access to all products<br />     - Variety of markets available with sufficient liquidity to do big trades<br />      - Derivatives/Spot/Prediction/FX products<br />     - Integration with other DeFi protocols<br />    - Regulatory compliance/clarity<br />       - Custody/Asset management<br />      - Rakeback for transaction fees<br />     - Best margin funding rate/leverage tools<br />     - Lowest interest fees<br />         - Best bid/offer spread<br />     - Low slippage<br />  - Easy onboarding<br />    - Capital efficiency(DeFi composability)<br /> - Loyalty programs</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>Broad institutional personas who interact with financial services and products can be classified as:</p>

<ul>
  <li>HNIs/Banks/Hedge Funds/Trading firms/ Market makers</li>
  <li>MNC Companies</li>
  <li>SME</li>
  <li>Governments/Treasuries</li>
</ul>

<p>They all want economic exposure to DeFi and to leverage the benefits of transacting on-chain (distributed/ decentralized/trust less/ permission less/cheaper / available/etc). 
Some requirements for the above actors:</p>

<p><u>Product Requirements</u>:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Everything from a retail speculator</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Risk Management</td>
      <td>Portfolio management</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Data and Analytics services</td>
      <td>Credit management</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Client relationship management</td>
      <td>Invoice financing</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Supply chain financing</td>
      <td>Equity financing</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>B2B payments and transfers</td>
      <td>Payroll</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Insurance</td>
      <td>Foreign exchange</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Principal protected yield</td>
      <td>Treasury management</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<hr />

<p>Products which solve core user requirements which overlap across the most number of personas have the highest likelihood of attaining scalable PMF (duh!). Now, we shall the investigate the user journey of these personas and try to understand the active participants in the value chain.</p>

<p>Profit pools are nothing but the total profit earned at all points along the value chain of an industry. When we analyse a value chain, it becomes imperative to define the boundaries of the sub-segment before digging deeper. Each of these segment profitability  may, for example, vary widely by customer group, product category, geographic market, or distribution channel. Moreover, the pattern of profit concentration in an industry is often very different from the pattern of revenue concentration. You can check this <a href="https://hbr.org/1998/05/how-to-map-your-industrys-profit-pool">article</a> on HBR to know how to map an industry’s pool.</p>

<p>In this section, we attempt to dig deeper into some open problem statements and propose possible solutions. In the next article, we shall investigate these participants from a profit/operating margin PoV to understand which problem statement is worth solving financially.</p>

<h5 id="user-journey">User Journey</h5>

<p>Lets pick an <strong>average retail DeFI investor</strong> and look at their user journey.</p>

<p>Intent to invest</p>
<ul>
  <li>High level actions in the user journey
    <ul>
      <li>On-boarding into a custody platform (interoperable platform)</li>
      <li>Infrastructure plumbing (equivalent of the payment rails)</li>
      <li>Fiat to crypto purchase</li>
      <li>Transfers/uses it on a Dapp</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Now, lets break down each of these steps and inspect the actors.</p>

<p><strong><u>Custody and Asset Management</u></strong></p>

<p>Similar to how fiat money is usually stored in savings accounts, central depositories, etc, crypto currencies have to stored in an online equivalent. Blockchains use digital signatures to secure money. Digital signatures are a pair of random keys, where one key is a “private key” and the other a “public key”. Through digital signatures, any person with the “private key” can “sign” a transaction and spend the digital currencies. Therefore, it is crucial to safeguard the “private key”. Some tech-savvy users of blockchains opt to safeguard this key themselves, and accept the risk of theft or loss of the key (and therefore the loss of their funds). In contrast, other blockchain users trust online wallets or exchanges with the safeguarding of their keys.</p>

<p>Custody management solutions overlap typically with the first step in the boarding process.Here, we are primarily focussing on the DeFi custody experience and not CeX related on-boarding flows.</p>

<p>Using the user requirements we looked at in the first step, lets see where the current gaps exist:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Recovery/Portability is cumbersome and user has to remember a key phrase usually.</li>
  <li>UX while using it across Dapps is broken (identity and auth).
    <ul>
      <li>It is a multi-step process. Sign/Approve spend/Transact. No standardized experience</li>
      <li>Transaction details are hard to understand
        <ul>
          <li>Txn costs are hard to predict</li>
          <li>Txn details include lengthy hex strings which don’t mean much to the user.</li>
          <li>Multiple confirmation steps and non-instantaneous transactions leads the user to confusion</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Managing multiple wallets/addresses is cumbersome</li>
  <li>From a first time web3 user perspective, its hard to understand what to do with the wallet after you install it on your phone. Onboarding through the specific Dapp directly has been more successful maybe for this reason.</li>
  <li>Interoperability across the ecosystem is not mature</li>
</ul>

<p>Let’s look at the current type of wallets and understand what they do:</p>

<p><strong>Self-custodial</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>User is responsible for their private keys
    <ul>
      <li>Typically stored locally in the user browser/device/mobile</li>
      <li>Recovery through a key phrase only</li>
      <li>Easy to create and discard.</li>
      <li>Examples:
        <ul>
          <li>Metamask</li>
          <li>Trustwallet</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Exchange wallets</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Investor allocates the control and management of private and public keys to exchanges.</li>
  <li>Gives control of keys in return for seamless access, lower fess but added counter party risk</li>
  <li>Examples of exchange wallets:
    <ul>
      <li>Coinbase</li>
      <li>Binance</li>
      <li>Vauld</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Third party custody</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Service providers storing digital assets on behalf of (business)customers</li>
  <li>Custom-defined features and controls for controlled management of the asset.</li>
  <li>Ideal for institutional crypto custody</li>
  <li>Enterprise security and insurance is usually offered</li>
  <li>Examples (usually institutional):
    <ul>
      <li>Bitgo</li>
      <li>Coinbase Prime</li>
      <li>
        <p>Instadapp sort of does this for retail.</p>
      </li>
      <li><em>Wallet as a service</em>
        <ul>
          <li>MPC wallets where the key is split between you and a third party.</li>
          <li>This means if you lose access to your private key, the key to your  wallet is still safe and recoverable. This helps with portability and availability across devices</li>
          <li>Sort of like multi-sig wallets where both the third party and you have to sign transactions</li>
          <li>Examples of wallets powered by this:
            <ul>
              <li>Coinbase dappbrowser</li>
              <li>Coindcx Okta</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>What can we work on?</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Onboarding and discovery solutions helping a new user navigate web3 DeFi products
    <ul>
      <li>Unified payments/transaction experience across chains/wallets</li>
      <li>Multi chain interoperable wallets
        <ul>
          <li>User ideally wants to live inside one wallet. Chains/protocols/etc should all be interoperable and talking to each other to provide a unified experience</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>MPC based wallets offer the ideal mix of good onboarding/operating experience without trade off on security/privacy</li>
</ul>

<p>Identity (Polygon ID, dynamic.xyz)</p>

<ul>
  <li>Identity and authentication while preserving privacy
    <ul>
      <li>Unified standards for interaction with protocols (authorization and authentication)
        <ul>
          <li>Ethereum foundation is working on account abstractions (<a href="https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-4337">EIP-4337</a>)
            <ul>
              <li>ZK proofs powered stealth address (where you can have a DeFi app level address which you can control but nobody else will know that you control it)</li>
              <li>Social recovery features</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Decentralized identity provider
        <ul>
          <li>Attach a name (ENS)</li>
          <li>Attach POAP or Proof of Humanity (privacy preserving using zk proofs)</li>
          <li>Imagine an identity provider who can log you into web2 apps also because we can basically verify identity and the users also have way more control over their data</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>These Dapps which the users want to interact with are built on top of blockchains which we will investigate in the next section. While an average CeX user may not even interact with blockchains (just buys on Coinbase and doesn’t do anything else), we are discussing about a web3 DeFi investor here. The user also doesn’t pay for these services as they are usually available for free but instead monetized through adjacent offerings. In the next section, we shall look at some of the core infra DeFi products as well.</p>

<p><strong><u>Infrastructure</u></strong></p>

<p>This is the plumbing needed for all of web3 to function. As an user, I don’t really care how what the name of the chain is or the infrastructure complexity. The only requirements here are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Availability across Dapps. (interoperability)</li>
  <li>Speed and security</li>
  <li>No overheads, cheap txn costs</li>
</ul>

<p>The participants here include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>L1/L2 chains. The block chains on which the Dapps are built on. Some core participants here include:
    <ul>
      <li>Mining
        <ul>
          <li>Mining pools
            <ul>
              <li>Mining as a service</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Node operators</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Staking
        <ul>
          <li>Validator Node operators</li>
          <li>Delegators
            <ul>
              <li>Staking as a service</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Searchers extracting MeV
        <ul>
          <li><img src="/assets/files/mev.png" alt="mev" class="img-responsive" /></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Multi chain protocols (shared liquidity/data layers)</li>
      <li>Identity (authentication and authorization) layers</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>What can we work on?</em>:</p>

<ul>
  <li>L1/L2 scaling and its subdivisions</li>
  <li>Staking
    <ul>
      <li>Staking as a service for institutions
        <ul>
          <li>Controls for returns/risk adjustments</li>
          <li>Taxation/Regulation/Compliance solutions based on geography</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Given that most chains are moving to PoS, staking providers become one of the key participants in the value chain. Loads of capital is going to be locked up and further hypothecated for use across DeFi. Proving a plumbing solution is imperative here.</li>
      <li>Multi chain staking + interop solve for staking
        <ul>
          <li>When I stake and get a liquid token in return, most of the user cases are siloed into the particular chain on which staking happens. As a staking provider, I should be able to provide cross chain liquid tokens which are easily transferrable.</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Block chain interoperability related problems
    <ul>
      <li>Given the fact that the user doesn’t bother with actual chain names and their respective trade offs and just wants a simple investing experience, it becomes imperative to find a solution to abstract away all the noise.</li>
      <li>Multi chain protocols primarily solve for sharing of data and liquidity across chains. Use cases include cross chain governance, basic state share, cross chain lending/borrowing</li>
      <li>Generic message transfer
        <ul>
          <li>Example: What does it mean for a lending protocol
            <ul>
              <li>Currently you put ETH as collateral (on ETH chain) and borrow. Then bridge it (to yield farming chain), swap (for yield token), yield farm, swap back again, bridge back again, then unlock collateral on ETH chain. Clearly this flow is broken.</li>
              <li>Ideal flow should be something like “lock collateral on ETH” chain, message goes to destination chain and you borrow directly there. Repay in destination chain and message comes back to ETH chain where your collateral gets unlocked.</li>
              <li>State transfer
                <ul>
                  <li>Transfer any piece of critical information across chain from your protocol.</li>
                  <li>Unified governance where votes are cast across chains</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Liquidity transfer layer
        <ul>
          <li>Instead of maintaining individual pair wise pools across chains (ETH on mainnet + ETH on Solana) to facilitate bridging, a more capital efficient way would be to do a common shared liquidity pool across all path ways.</li>
          <li>Collateral bridging
            <ul>
              <li>How to power Dapps to have their own liquidity transfer layer across chain
                <ul>
                  <li>aave v3 has aave portal</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Yield aggregation
      - Ultimately user just wants to deploy on the most profitable farm</li>
          <li>DeFi apps
            <ul>
              <li>Uniswap doesnt want users to leave the platform to go to a bridge and the come back for swapping. It should be able to provide a much unified experience</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Current ecosytem
        <ul>
          <li>Middle chain
            <ul>
              <li>You start with two chains which are atomic and have their own state. Most solutions involve putting in a chain in middle for communicating data. The middle chain comes to consensus on the validity of the transactions and writes to the destination chain
                <ul>
                  <li>You are implicitly trusting the middle chains which makes a big honeypot. Polynetwork is one example</li>
                  <li>Thorchain sort of does this with their common layer where all assets are trading against RUNE</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
              <li>Hub - Spoke model
                <ul>
                  <li>System where everything is routed through the middle hub in the center (Polkadot)</li>
                  <li>Entire security requirements are offloaded to the hub</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Cosmos IBC stuff
            <ul>
              <li>Takes the block header of all blocks and write it on the destination chain. Repeats the process vice versa</li>
              <li>Once you have the entire block history, you can validate
                <ul>
                  <li>Very expensive to do this</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>LayerZero/Router protocol (interop as a service)
            <ul>
              <li>Take single block, stream it on demand and validate it on other chain. Mostly a two part system with a oracle and a relayer. Oracle takes a block header and submits to destination chain and you can plug this oracle layer to different oracles like chainlink etc. The relayer simply takes the transaction proof and submits it on the destination chain.</li>
              <li>Each Dapp can wrap their contract with these to enable instant interop across any L1 to L2 EVM compatible or not
                <ul>
                  <li>Security is split across multiple parties (multiple oracles and relayers)</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>CeX are basically interop solves as well</li>
          <li>Native bridges and bridge aggregators (socket.tech)</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Every chain is going to become interoperable and future users onboarded aren’t even going to recognize the difference between yield farming on Solana vs ETH. Wallet experience and Dapp discovery is going to change because of this.  L1/L2 chains which support the most amount of modularity would eventually be best suited to capture this future .</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>MeV aware solutions</li>
  <li>Blockchain API and data providers
    <ul>
      <li>Analytics on blockchain</li>
      <li>Providing blockchain as a service</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>Above DeFi actors capture majority of the value in this step. They are directly/in-directly involved with every user transacting on chain and thereby also are at an intersection of the most value transferred. In the next post, we shall look at some key metrics to evaluate these actors across the value chain.</p>

<p>Now the user has a wallet and connected to a chain to transact. Its time to move on to looking at the next participants in this value chain</p>

<p><strong><u>On-Ramp and exchanges</u></strong></p>

<p>Remembering that our user is a <strong>retail DeFi investor</strong>, lets look at some user requirements and pain points:</p>
<ul>
  <li>User just wants to convert his/her fiat into crypto</li>
  <li>Wants to pay the least amount of fees (slippage, txn fees) and wants the best price</li>
</ul>

<p>Some participants here:</p>

<ul>
  <li>KYC(if you are going to be regulated anyway, doublick click here for proof for identity/etc like polygon id/ platforms adhering to regulatory compliance are the first step in the on-boarding process (application include aadhar)</li>
  <li>On-ramp solutions which is the primary place to convert fiat to crypto
    <ul>
      <li>Exchanges usually interact with tradFi banking/payment system to take in fiat money</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Exchange + Liquidity to convert fiat to crypto (swaps)
    <ul>
      <li>Liquidity protocols providing the markets for the user to trade in.</li>
      <li>Stable coins</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Gateway products which convert fiat to crypto (banking integrations)</li>
  <li>Stable coin issuers (primarily purchased first because of their ubiquity in web3)</li>
</ul>

<p>what problems to work on?</p>

<ul>
  <li>Reduce the number of steps needed to convert crypto through block chain interop</li>
  <li>Geography aware KYC solutions</li>
</ul>

<p><strong><u>Dapp interaction</u></strong></p>

<p>Now that the user has converted his/her to fiat to crypto, lets look at the journey to invest in Dapps.
As an user, my primary requirements would be:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Investing
    <ul>
      <li>Yield farming
        <ul>
          <li>Staking pools</li>
          <li>Lending/Borrowing</li>
          <li>Liquidity pool
            <ul>
              <li>Yield aggregators/boosters/auto compounders</li>
              <li>Bribes/Governance co-ordination</li>
              <li>Derivatives</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>For the next wave of Defi products to be bigger than the previous/current state we need an influx of new set of users who have never used these products before. Making these investment Dapp retail-newbie friendly is paramount.</p>

<h5 id="summary">Summary</h5>

<p>As we look across the value chain of a <strong>retail investor</strong>, we notice that major value transacts across these players:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Custody management</li>
  <li>Staking</li>
  <li>Blockchain interop</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, depending on which business we are trying to enter, you can further double click to understand all adjacent offerings as well. A liquid staking service would eventually move into wallets to capture more TVL or approach the same problem from the perspective of an institution to offer DeFi products with access controls for risk profile/taxation/regulations etc.</p>

<p>Checkout my other related posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/09/tornado-cash-block.html">We should all have something to hide - Tornado cash takedown</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives.html">Option protocols in DeFi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/27/web3-gaming.html">Blockchain gaming - Current state</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The first section of the article inspects the various user personas interacting with DeFi protocols and their individual requirements. The second section identifies various products which solve for these use cases. We mostly look for on-chain use cases which already have a reasonable amount of adoption. This post simply surfaces the various participants across the value chain and identifies open problems. Some cutting-edge novel cases with nascent adoption might get overlooked. Nevertheless, we keep an eye out for unsolved/potential growth segments and see what we can build there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Make Poker fun again</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make Poker fun again" /><published>2022-08-22T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-08-22T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/22/profit-growth-gamification.html"><![CDATA[<h4 id="introduction">Introduction</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Lets face it, poker has become a commoditized game/product where most poker platforms look like skins of each other. There is hardly any differentiation in the products and all of them simply focus on the betting/gambling function of the game while a human centric focus on the user journey takes a back seat.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>This is primarily due to the fact that human focussed features/design elements particularly don’t drive revenue directly. However, they make the product more fun to indulge in.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Unfortunately most platforms are just laser focussed betting tools which are designed to get the user wagering as soon as possible. Its almost like 2000s traders made poker software products.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Poker’s market cap is not growing at pace with the rest of the real money gaming ecosystem. E-sports and casual gaming are growing much faster (on a bigger base too) compared to real money gaming(and especially poker. Online Gaming has become ubiquitous especially in the post COVID world where people are staying more and more indoor and interacting with others online. online gaming has surpassed from being just an entertainment thing used by a bunch of geeks to mainstream extension of one’s identify online. It one of the <a href="https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2022/07/06/2475487/0/en/Online-Gaming-Market-Size-to-Achieve-USD-132-Billion-by-2030-Growing-at-10-2-CAGR-Fueled-by-Massive-Investments-in-the-Gaming-Industry-Exclusive-Report-by-Acumen-Research-and-Consu.html">top categories</a> online in <a href="https://www.businessofapps.com/data/fortnite-statistics/">terms of spends</a> as well.</p>

<h4 id="why-is-growth-important">Why is growth important?</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Opportunity cost of investing in poker vs other games/sectors. While poker is generally a profitable vertical for RMG (real money gaming) companies, the “real” value of the vertical/game is usually measured by the future cash flows which in turn is determined by your growth rate.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In the stages of a business from early PMF to a scalable PMF to a scalable profitable PMF, its very important that the vertical displays potential for scalability much before we think about profitability. Poker usually starts making money(profits) early on but scalability is still a question mark.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>As part of my job, my responsibility is to explore ways to grow the poker ecosystem in India. With everybody playing games, its not a leap to suggest incorporating certain gamification elements to make poker more enjoyable.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>There are bunch of vectors to drive growth. The direct way includes discounting, increased marketing burn etc whereas the harder way includes gamification, offering more products/services (cross-selling), community building, identifying profit pools in the value chain and building around them, etc</p>

<p>We want to craft a user experience which is much more than just <strong>Deposit Money-&gt; Select table -&gt; Start betting</strong>.</p>

<p>This article focuses on bring elements of games into poker to make it more fun and thereby drive growth. Using the <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/gamification-behavioral-design-the-octalysis-framework/">Octalysis framework</a>, we can look at some possible elements and understand how they may be applicable to poker. While its hard to wrap the actual betting mechanics/UX into a gamified journey, we can look at other adjacent flows too. The key elements of the framework include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>A bigger narrative/meaning</li>
  <li>Feeling of progress and accomplishments</li>
  <li>Creative user participation</li>
  <li>Sense of ownership</li>
  <li>Social influence</li>
  <li>FOMO</li>
  <li>Unpredictability</li>
  <li>Loss avoidance</li>
</ol>

<h5 id="a-bigger-narrativemeaning">A bigger narrative/meaning</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>It is the Core Drive where a player believes that he is doing something greater than himself or he was “chosen” to do something. Attaching meaning to playing the game becomes an intrinsic motivating factor for the player</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>We see a lot of companies playing to this sentiment like CRED(a lifestyle company), D2C brands, early Spotify (younger cool kids music app), etc</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>While regular games have storylines, fictious identities, in poker, making the player win something big in a practice/tutorial step, or in the first session thereby making the player feel “chosen” creates a welcoming atmosphere for new poker players.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Currently poker is also viewed mainly as gambling in India. Maybe organising Poker as an India wide talent competition under the assumption that people view winning the competition as a prestigious thing helps. It also creates social influence among your peers too.  This is definitely the case with WSOP. Also  creating content around the skill aspect of poker and popularising it would help change the narrative on how poker is viewed in our Tier-2 or Tier-3 cities.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="feeling-of-progress-and-accomplishments">Feeling of progress and accomplishments</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Development &amp; Accomplishment is the internal drive of making progress, developing skills, and eventually overcoming challenges.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This is one of the easiest to design for and already widely implemented across the industry. In poker, common implementations include:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Challenges/goals/tasks which are staggered with multiple sub-levels incentivising the user to finish a set of tasks.</li>
      <li>Anything else to make the user feel that they are making progress:
        <ul>
          <li>Skill scores</li>
          <li>Limited winner/time bound leader boards</li>
          <li>Lavish use of progress bars</li>
          <li>A super high rake back tier given only to the top 5 players on the platform</li>
          <li>Special locked emojis/effects/time banks etc</li>
          <li>Special custom effects for winning pots/losing pots which can be  customised for a particular players</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="creative-user-participation">Creative user participation</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Empowerment of Creativity &amp; Feedback is when users are engaged in a creative process where they have to repeatedly figure things out and try different combinations. People not only need ways to express their creativity, but they need to be able to see the results of their creativity, receive feedback, and respond in turn.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>We need a feature with tight feedback loop which takes in user input and something which preferably has a creative element attached to it. IKEA furniture have this element of self-assembly which makes the user care for the product.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>In poker, some common methods include
        <ul>
          <li>User avatar customization (filters,emojis)</li>
          <li>Custom table/card and background themes, social features ,etc. making their version of the client unique for them</li>
          <li>Allowing users to design their own card/table themes is unexplored currently though</li>
          <li>Social features (creative pre-defined voice chats, meme based emojis etc) which the user can use to express various sentiments inside the game</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Waze (the traffic app) intelligently uses user generated content where the platform users feel a sense of ownership in keeping the data accurate and up to date.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="sense-of-ownership">Sense of ownership</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>This is the drive where users are motivated because they feel like they own something. When a player feels ownership, she innately wants to make what she owns better and own even more.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Also, if a person spends a lot of time to customize her profile or her avatar, she automatically feels more ownership towards it too. Same applies to user earned virtual points/goods which can be be exchanged for other goods. We see a lot of companies implementing their own inhouse tokens/coins.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In fact, this is (token sale) is one of the most common GTM strategies in the web3 space. The assumption is that with early community ownership, folks are incentivised to drive product adoption and growth.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In poker we want to make the user feel that they own their identity/progress inside the game.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Custom avatar(which the user spent time customizing/assembling) which can be minted/exchanged for something else</li>
      <li>In-game coins which can used for
        <ul>
          <li>As a proxy for giving rake back</li>
          <li>Exchangeable for real-money, virtual goods or even physical goods</li>
          <li>Give power to the user to boost a pot size (like splash the pot which is user controlled. <a href="https://www.runitonce.eu/features/splash-the-pot/#:~:text=At%20Run%20It%20Once%2C%20we,collected%20back%20on%20the%20tables.">Reference</a>)</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="social-influence">Social influence</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>This drive incorporates all the social elements that drive people, including: mentorship, acceptance, social responses, companionship, as well as competition and envy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Often implemented in the form of social events, group/team competitions, contests (with a lot of PR for the winners), televising etc by most companies. This is usually well executed as well as I see most platforms having a strong social media presence.</p>
    <ul>
      <li>When you see your friend winning big in a poker competition, you automatically feel like playing the game too.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="fomo">FOMO</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Scarcity, impatience or basically the drive of wanting something because you can’t have it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Often executed in the form of chosen waiting lists (Ultrahuman which onboarded only certain people early day), gatekeeping for certain users (CRED, early Facebook), etc. In poker we can</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Exclusive private high stake tables allowed for only certain players</li>
      <li>Invite only tournaments and other events</li>
      <li>Even basic tournament prize structure which pays out only top 5 players and tapes out super fast. TLB with limited winners</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="unpredictability">Unpredictability</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Generally, this is a harmless drive of wanting to find out what will happen next. If you don’t know what’s going to happen, your brain is engaged and you think about it often. Many people watch movies or read novels because of this drive. <strong>However, this drive is also the primary factor behind gambling addiction</strong>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Lotteries, sweepstakes, slot machines, scratch cards work for said reason although they are sometimes confused against achievements/badges. In poker, its commonly implemented as</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Different animations for turn/river cards trying to peak the user curiosity</li>
      <li>Random splash pots where pots are randomly boosted sometimes</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h5 id="loss-avoidance">Loss avoidance</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>This core drive is based upon the avoidance of something negative happening.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Commonly executed by making the user lose previous progress, emphasising the sunk cost, rake back tiers which expire,  bonus points which expire etc. Most reactivation campaigns play to this sentiment.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h4 id="summary">Summary</h4>

<p>The core idea is to tailor make features which apply these concepts for <strong>your</strong> product, <strong>your</strong> community, <strong>your</strong> currency etc.</p>

<p>Poker products need not be just simple betting/gambling platforms. Poker can become a <em>fun</em>, <em>skill-based</em> game where people share their progress, discuss strategies, buy/sell in-game loyalty points, compare skill-scores, set avatars and also brag about their winnings.</p>

<p>If you liked reading my post, you can check other similar posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/27/web3-gaming.html">Blockchain gaming - Current state</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/06/15/gtoinspector-startup.html">GTO Inspector - My attempt at building an online business</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Option protocols in DeFi</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Option protocols in DeFi" /><published>2022-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-08-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/15/defi-derivatives.html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a summary of all the options products available in the DeFi space. I embarked on doing a bit of research after I wanted to hedge my LP positions given the current volatile market and the impending <a href="https://ethereum.org/en/upgrades/merge/">merge</a>.</p>

<p>Before going ahead, it helps the reader to have  a basic understanding of what options/futures are. You can read a basic primer <a href="https://zerodha.com/varsity/module/option-theory/">here</a> from <a href="https://zerodha.com/">Zerodha</a> which elaborates on the fundamentals of an options contract in TradFi.</p>

<p>One of the main differences between TradFi options and DeFi options is the additional component of a liquidity pool. Since we can’t have orderbooks (due to limited TPS, available block space etc) in DeFi, liquidity providers come together to provide liquidity to the pool in return for earning some yield. You can think of these LP’s as the equivalent of market makers(banks/hedge funds/prop trading shops) in TradFi.</p>

<p>Most of these product are inspired from the equivalent TradFi products and follow along closely in terms of their equivalent implementation.</p>

<p><a href="https://perp.com">Perp.com</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>One of the first on-chain futures which were composable. Deribit/Bybit might predate them but they we based on CEX’s.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Everlasting contracts with no expiry. Imagine a NIFTY futures contract without an expiry date.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In TradFi, the price of the futures contract is usually different from the underlying’s prices and converges to the value of the underlying on the expiry date. The deviation is caused by the risk free interest rate and/or any dividend given out by the underlying before the expiry period. Since we don’t have expiry dates here, we need a mechanism to price these contracts. Enter funding rates which the longs pay the shorts to help keep the futures price close to it underlying.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/files/funding.png" alt="perp" class="img-responsive" /></p>

<p>Basically funding rates will always tend towards zero as other market participants (traders/arbitrageurs/etc) will take advantage of the rate by going long when its negative or going short when its positive, thereby aligning the price of the of the perp with the underlying. 
If the funding rate is positive, you can short perps and buy ETH on the spot market for a delta neutral strategy. A bunch of start-ups have automated this trade:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Diamond protocol does this cash and carry strategy (as a vault) using an algorithm to find the best rebalance frequency for the current market and rebalance automatically for the vault’s depositors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Due to the fact that these primitives are composable, there are also tokens which represent the above trade. Holding them would earn you funding payment without exposure to price. $BYE (Basis Yield ETH) is one such token.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.opyn.co/">Opyn</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>I stumbled onto them quite late (by crypto standards) while reading this <a href="https://www.paradigm.xyz/2021/08/power-perpetuals">paradigm article</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>While they have “normal” perp options, I am interested in power perps (power contracts are basically attached to the square of the underlying’s price. If BTC goes 2x, the power^2 perp goes, 4x) because of their non linear returns similar to how options behave</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Squeeth (that’s how they call their square perp) doesn’t have expiry dates or even strike prices for that matter.They run distributed option vaults (DOVs) with their inhouse product Squeeth instead of “regular” options these days.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>For detailed payoff diagrams and explanations on how Squeeth behaves during different market conditions, you can check this article <a href="https://medium.com/opyn/the-best-market-conditions-to-squeeth-3e92d868b533">here</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.hegic.co/">Hegic</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>They run a liquidity pool marketplace for operating an American style option. American options are slightly expensive than European options for the fact that they can be exercised anytime.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Options trade in secondary markets where market makers/option writers can define the price of the option using their internal model. It looks like Hegic controls the IV variable and thereby the price of option as well.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Options purchased on this platform are not composable meaning, I cant trade/use this position somewhere else in the DeFi ecosystem</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.zeta.markets/">Zeta</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Given really long block times and the inability to structure atomic trades, most of these option writers require full collateralization. However, due to faster L2’s and alternative L1’s going mainstream, we can now have faster M2M update which will help us price our options better which in turn means ability to offer under collateralized options</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Zeta provides under-collateralized options with an on-chain pricing engine and margin system.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>While the above platforms mostly work on fundamental primitives, there are also a lot of companies providing pre-made option strategies for retail participants to invest in. These are particularly attractive to the less-complicated user who wants a quicker investing/gambling experience.</p>

<h5 id="distributed-option-vaults-dovs">Distributed Option Vaults (DOVs)</h5>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>DOVs are a new form of structured product which are mostly a collection of pre-defined option strategies. DOV’s are pretty important because they are able to democratize access to options without the user needing to understand complex jargon, choosing strikes/expiry or the risk of losing a lot.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In TradFI, a specific combination of derivatives are selected, packaged and sold to clients looking for custom non-traditional payout curves. These clients are usually HNI’s/institutions and the intermediary (banks mostly) charge a fee for setting this up.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Let’s look at how these products are structured in the DeFi space:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ribbon.finance/">Ribbon Finance</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>DOVs, with most of them running a basic covered call strategy. The call options are minted from the Opyn vault.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>They usually run covered call or cash covered put strategies which is a great on-ramp solve for retail traders looking to get some exposure in derivatives.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Imagine Zerodha having a one click auto compounding covered call strategy against all your stock holdings. That would be really convenient.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://friktion.fi/">Friktion</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Volt1</strong>: This is a basic DOV with covered call strategy on SOL, BTC, ETH etc.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Volt2</strong>: Cash secured puts on the same assets as above.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Volt3</strong>: Deltra neutral  crab strategy. In TradFi, I would usually express this sentiment with a stradle or a strangle. Here, they use power perps to come up with a novel way to delta hedge. Payoff looks something like this:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><img src="/assets/files/payoff.png" alt="payoff" class="img-responsive" /></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Volt4</strong>: Basis yield (delta neutral strategy which is used for eating the funding rate in perps as discussed above). During a positive funding environment, this strategy goes short on the perp contract and long on the spot to earn the funding rate and vice verse during negative funding environments.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.brahma.fi/">BrahmaFi</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>PMUSDC
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>A simple vault which does LP yield farming (boost LP rewards through convex and reinvest back into LP pool. sort of like yearn finance) with an added addition of taking a momentum trade using the yield on Lyra/perp.com</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>The extra edge in this strategy comes mainly from their internal momentum bot. Otherwise, its just a yearn finance strategy with extra fees. They used to do the same trade on GMX earlier</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>There are a lot more derivate platforms which further build on top of yield aggregators, DOVs etc. We shall have a look at them in the next post.</p>

<p>If you like it, check out my other posts too:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://rnikhil.com/2022/08/09/tornado-cash-block.html">We should all have something to hide - Tornado cash takedown</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Nikhil</name><email>contact@rnikhil.com</email></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post is a summary of all the options products available in the DeFi space. I embarked on doing a bit of research after I wanted to hedge my LP positions given the current volatile market and the impending merge.]]></summary></entry></feed>